ShadwoPlay Tutorial text
========================

_This text is used in the Main.storyboard paged tutorial views._

EN
--

### ShadowPlay

ShadowPlay is an exploration of architecture and light in outdoor spaces through sound.

### Setup

Using a bicycle-mounted smartphone as a brightness sensor and a bluetooth speaker, the mottled patterns of light and shadow become the musical score as one rides along city streets.

### Camera

Place device in bicycle mount with a clear view for the active camera (either front or rear).

It's Ok if part of the camera is covered, for example by the bicycle wheel, as long as most of the ground (or sky) is visible.

### Calibrate

To calibrate the brightness detection:

1. Open ... -> Calibrate
2. Press the Start button
3. Roll bike over/under both light and dark areas
4. Press Stop button when finished

The brightness range bar on the top of the screen shows the current value in pink and the calibration range in turquoise.

When calibrated, the current value pink line should stay within the turquoise range. 

If you move to a new place or the light changes, re-calibration may be necessary.

### Scenes

Choose an audio scene from the Scenes table which defines the live sonification of the changes in brightness.

Some scenes use overall brightness, others detect the transitions between light and shadow, some work with direct input, while others are more subtle.

You can also write your own scenes using the open source Pure Data computer music environment.

See ... -> Info for details.

Have fun!

### Acknowledgements

Supported through the UNESCO City of Media Arts Karlsruhe as well as through the City of Karlsruhe.

Scene contributions by Sofy Yuditskaya and Damian Stewart.

DE
--

### ShadowPlay

ShadowPlay ist eine Erkundung von Architektur und Licht in Außenräumen durch Klang.

### Einrichten

Mit einem am Fahrrad befestigten Smartphone als Helligkeitssensor und einem Bluetooth-Lautsprecher werden die gesprenkelten Licht- und Schattenmuster zur Musik, während man die Straßen der Stadt entlangfährt.

### Kamera

Platzieren Sie das Gerät in einer Fahrradhalterung mit freier Sicht für die aktive Kamera (entweder vorne oder hinten).

Es ist in Ordnung, wenn ein Teil der Kamera verdeckt ist, z. B. durch das Fahrradrad, solange der größte Teil des Bodens (oder des Himmels) sichtbar ist.

### Kalibrieren

So kalibrieren Sie die Helligkeitserkennung:

1. Öffnen Sie ... -> Kalibrieren
2. Drücken Sie die Schaltfläche Start
3. Fahren Sie mit dem Fahrrad über/unter helle und dunkle Bereiche
4. Drücken Sie die Stopp-Taste, wenn Sie fertig sind.

Der Helligkeitsbereichsbalken oben auf dem Bildschirm zeigt den aktuellen Wert in rosa und den Kalibrierungsbereich in türkis an.

Wenn Sie kalibriert sind, sollte die rosa Linie des aktuellen Werts innerhalb des türkisfarbenen Bereichs bleiben. 

Wenn Sie an einen neuen Ort ziehen oder sich die Lichtverhältnisse ändern, kann eine erneute Kalibrierung erforderlich sein.

### Scenes

Wählen Sie eine Audioszene aus der Tabelle Szenen aus, die die Live-Sonifikation der Helligkeitsänderungen definiert.

Einige Szenen verwenden die Gesamthelligkeit, andere erkennen die Übergänge zwischen Licht und Schatten, einige arbeiten mit direkter Eingabe, während andere subtiler sind.

Sie können auch Ihre eigenen Szenen schreiben, indem Sie die Open-Source-Computermusikumgebung Pure Data verwenden.

Siehe ... -> Info für Details.

Viel Vergnügen!

### Danksagung

Unterstützt durch die UNESCO City of Media Arts Karlsruhe sowie durch die Stadt Karlsruhe.

Szenische Beiträge von Sofy Yuditskaya und Damian Stewart.
